>> Long live Animal Farm.
>> And after the singing of Beasts of England, the animals were dismissed.
Afterwards, Squealer made a round of the farm and set the animals' minds at rest.
He assured them that the resolution against engaging in trade and using
money had never been passed or even suggested.
It was pure imagination, probably traceable in the beginning to lies circulated by Snowball.
A few animals still felt faintly doubtful, but Squealer asked them shrewdly,
>> "Are you certain that this is not something that you have dreamed,
comrades? Have you any record of such a resolution? Is it written down anywhere?
>> And since it was certainly true that nothing of the kind existed in writing,
the animals were satisfied that they had been mistaken.
Every Monday, Mr. Whimper visited the farm as had been arranged. He was a
sly-looking little man with side whiskers, a solicitor in a very small way of business,
but sharp enough to have realized earlier than anyone else that Animal
Farm would need a broker and that the commissions would be worth having.
The animals watched his coming and going with a kind of dread and avoided him as
much as possible.
Nevertheless, the sight of Napoleon on all fours delivering orders to Whimper
who stood on two legs roused their pride and partly reconciled them to the new arrangement.
Their relations with the human race were now not quite the same as they had been before.
The human beings did not hate Animal Farm any less now that it was
prospering. Indeed, they hated it more than ever.
Every human being held it as an article of faith that the farm would go bankrupt
sooner or later and, above all, that the windmill would be a failure.
They would meet in the public houses and prove to one another by means of
diagrams that the windmill was bound to fall down or that if it did stand up,
then that it would never work.
And yet, against their will, they had developed a certain respect for the
efficiency with which the animals were managing their own affairs.
One symptom of this was that they had begun to call Animal Farm by its proper
name and ceased to pretend that it was called the Manor Farm.
They had also dropped their championship of Jones who had given up hope of
getting his farm back and gone to live in another part of the county.
Except through Whymper, there was as yet no contact between Animal Farm and the
outside world. But there were constant rumors that Napoleon was about to enter
into a definite business agreement either with Mr. Pilkington of Foxwood or
with Mr. Frederick of Pinchfield.
But never, it was noticed, with both simultaneously.
It was about this time that the pigs suddenly moved into the farmhouse and
took up their residence there.
Again, the animals seemed to remember that a resolution against this had been
passed in the early days. And again, Squealer was able to convince them that
this was not the case.
"It was absolutely necessary," he said, "that the pigs, who were the brains of
the farm, should have a quiet place to work in.
It was also more suited to the dignity of the leader, for of late he had taken
to speaking of Napoleon under the title of leader,
to live in a house than in a mere sty."
Nevertheless, some of the animals were disturbed when they heard that the pigs
not only took their meals in the kitchen and used the drawing room as a
recreation room, but also slept in the beds.
Boxer passed it off as usual with >> "Napoleon is always right."
>> But Clover, who thought she remembered a definite ruling against beds,
went to the end of the barn and tried to puzzle out the Seven Commandments, which
were inscribed there.
Finding herself unable to read more than individual letters, she fetched Muriel.
>> "Muriel, read me the Fourth Commandment.
Does it not say something about never sleeping in a bed.
>> With some difficulty, Muriel spelt it out.
>> It says, "No animal shall sleep in a bed with sheets."
>> Curiously enough, Clover had not remembered that the fourth commandment mentioned sheets.
But as it was there on the wall, it must have done so. And Squealer, who happened
to be passing at this moment, attended by two or three dogs, was able to put
the whole matter in its proper perspective.
>> "You have heard then, comrades, that we pigs now sleep in the beds of the
farmhouse. And why not? You did not suppose, surely, that there was ever a
ruling against beds. A bed merely means a place to sleep in. A pile of straw in
a stall is a bed, properly regarded. The rule was against sheets, which are a
human invention. We have removed the sheets from the farmhouse beds and sleep
between blankets. And very comfortable beds they are, too. But not more
comfortable than we need, I can tell you, comrades, with all the brain work
we have to do nowadays. You would not rob us of our repose, would you,
comrades? You would not have us too tired to carry out our duties. Surely,
none of you wishes to see Jones back."
>> The animals reassured him on this point immediately, and no more was said about
the pigs sleeping in the farmhouse beds.
And when, some days afterwards, it was announced that from now on the pigs